<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
  as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Holiday Demo</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Holiday example movie</title>
      <p>
			The movie shows the first steps you can do after the installation of NetBpm. 
			You will see how to deploy and start workflows. 
			Further on you will be informed about the functionality of the NetBpm Web application. 
			But the web application is only an example for the integration of the core functionality in a custom application. 
			It also is possible to integrate that core functionality in a winForm application.
      </p>
      <p>
			 <a href="http://www.netbpm.org/movie/holiday/holiday.html">start movie</a>
      </p>
      <p>
			If you got curious after watching the video try it yourself at the demo side.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Holiday Demo</title>
      <p>
			You can find a demo application at <a href="http://gruenauer.homedns.org/netbpm/intro/index.rails">http://gruenauer.homedns.org/netbpm/intro/index.rails</a>. 
			This is not a permanent website. If the side is down please wait an hour, 
			if this does not help please inform me by mail (Philipp at netbpm dot org).
      </p>
      <p>
			The demo shows only a small workflow with a webgui and not the integration functionalities of NetBpm. 
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Short Description</title>
      <p>
			The holiday process allows users to manage planned absences. Every employee is able to request holiday. 
			The requester has to enter the startdate, enddate and a comment. Then this request is presented to the boss of the requester. 
			The boss evaluates. If the holiday is approved, both the HR-responsible and the requester will be informed.
			If the holiday is disapproved, only the requester will be notified 
      </p>
      <p>Let me introduce the people in my fictive organisation used for demo purposes: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Albert Einstein</li>
        <li>Carl Gauss</li>
        <li>Pierre De Fermat</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Albert Einstein and Carl Gauss are both in the 'Research and Development'-department.</p>
      <p>Carl Gauss is the boss of the 'Research and Development'-department.</p>
      <p>Pierre De Fermat is the 'HR-responsible' for the 'Research and Development'-department.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
